Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Certificates 1700-1991 PR 014
New-York Historical Society
- Series X: Historical, 1823-1980
  - American Historical Association, 1930 (Folder FF41)
  - American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society, 1912 (Folder FF41)
  - Alexander Hamilton National Memorial Association, 1903 (Folder FF42)
  - Bunker Hill Monument Association, circa 1823 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ulysses S. Grant Monument Association, 1897 (Folder FF34)
  - Hoboken Soldiers Monument Association, undated (Folder FF34)
  - Abraham Lincoln Societies, 1869-1928 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - New-York Historical Society, 1846-1974, undated (Folder FF NYHS 1 - 4)
    Additional membership certificates from N-YHS can be found in the institutional archive: New-York Historical Society membership records (NYHS-RG 9).
  - Roosevelt Memorial Association, circa 1920 (Folder FF34)
  - Society for the Preservation of Antique Motor Fire Apparatus in America, 1980 (Folder FF39)
  - Soldier's Monument Park Association of Schuylkill County, circa 1887 (Folder FF34)
  - George Washington Societies, 1923-1938, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Roger Williams Monument Association, circa 1860 (Folder FF34)
  - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, circa 1922 (Folder FF34)
- Series XI: Humanitarian, 1700-1910
  This series contains membership certificates for the New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, the Woman's Central Association of Relief, Cape Palmas Female Orphan Asylum Society, the Lawrence Benevolent Institution of Pennsylvania, the U.S. Sanitary Commission, the New-Jersey Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery.
  Certificates for the New York Marine Society, a group formed to provide assistance to widows and children of deceased sailors, include both reproductions and originals with wax seals. There are also certificates from other maritime organizations that provided assistance to sailors and their families.
  Of special interest is a certificate for completion of an apprenticeship at the New York House of Refuge, circa 1870.
  - American Female Guardian Society and Home for the Friendless, 1857 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - American Seamen's Friend Society, 1848, undated (Folder FF36)
  - American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, 1885 (Folder FF35)
  - Benevolent Institution of Pennsylvania, 1825 (Folder FF35)
  - Brooklyn and Long Island Sanitary Fair, 1864 (Folder FF35)
  - Cape Palmas Female Orphan Asylum Society, 1854 (Folder FF35)
  - Department of Health (New York City). Little Mothers League, 1910 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    Gift, New York Genealogical and Biographical Society, January 1992. Added to finding aid, January 2022.
  - New Jersey Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - New York House of Refuge, circa 1870 (Folder FF35)
  - New York Marine Society, 1700-1862 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, 1876, 1879 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newport Marine Society, undated (Folder FF36)
  - Provident Society of the State of New York, 1807 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sandy Hook Pilot's Charitable Fund, 1855 (Folder FF36)
  - Womans Central Association for Relief, 1866 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
- Series XII: Legal, 1809-1936
  This series includes birth, marriage and death certificates, passports, and certificates of admission to the bar. Some are on parchment and include wax or foil seals. Also included are leases, receipts, a deed for land in the Dakota Territories, and a certificate from the London Trade Marks Registry Office.
  Of special interest is an ornate lithograph recording the marriage of Henry Lockwood and Zana Rowland in 1885. Cartes de visite of the bride and groom are attached to the verso.
  Also of note is a hand-lettered document from the State of New York Executive Chamber. The certificate, created in 1913, is affixed with the pen that was used to sign a bill regarding the Highway Act into law.
  - Admission to the Bar, 1809-1914 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Admission to the Bar, 1883-1926 (Folder FF37)
  - Birth Certificates, circa 1850 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cemetery Deeds, 1959 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Citizenship Papers, 1831-1925 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Citizenship Papers, 1888 (Folder FF 37-A)
  - Death Certificates, 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Land Patents, 1889 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Leases, 1836, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Legal Advisory Boards, 1917-1919, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legal Societies, 1850-1927, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Licenses-Professional/Business, 1864-1931 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Marriage Certificates, 1856-1917 (Folder FF38)
  - Notices of Probate, 1881 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Passports, 1869 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    issued to Daniel Parish Jr.
  - Passports, 1831-1925 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Trademark Registers, 1879 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
- Series XIII: Medical, 1816-1946, 1970s?
  This series contains certificates related to the medical profession, including diplomas from medical schools, certificates of membership in medical societies, and registrations to practice medicine.
  Certificates of membership from the Society of the New York Hospital are made out to John McComb, John McComb Jr., and James W. Beekman.
  - Commissions- Federal- Surgeons, 1890, 1911 (Folder FF39)
  - Commissions-State of New York- Surgeons, 1816, 1818 (Folder FF39)
  - Hospitals-American Ambulance Hospital of Paris, 1914 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-Broad Street Hospital, 1922 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-Floating Hospital of St. John's Guild, 1874-1876 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-New York Eye and Ear Infirmary, 1878, 1893 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-New-York Hospital, 1817-1850 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-Roosevelt Hospital, 1854-1924 (Folder FF40)
  - Hospitals-St. Luke's Hospital, 1885 (Folder FF40)
  - Licenses, Registers and Diplomas-Register of Physicians and Surgeons, New York County, 1869-1914 (Folder FF41)
  - Licenses, Registers and Diplomas- State Board of Medical Examiners of New Jersey, 1921 (Folder FF41)
  - Licenses, Registers and Diplomas-New York Board for Examination and Licensing, 1871 (Folder FF41)
  - Licenses, Registers and Diplomas-New York State University, 1852-1913 (Folder FF41)
  - Licenses, Registers and Diplomas- New York Medical College, 1856-1859 (Folder FF41)
  - Medical Associations-American College of Surgeons, 1821-1924 (Folder FF42)
  - Medical Associations-American National Red Cross, 1916-1946 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Medical Associations-Medical Association of the Greater City of New York, 1899 (Folder FF42)
  - Medical Associations-Medical Society of the County of New York, 1898 (Folder FF42)
  - Medical Associations-National Association of Registered Nursing Homes, circa 1970s? (Folder FF42)
    Grade A accreditation awarded to Townsend Sanitarium.
  - Medical Associations-New York Medico Legal Society, 1872 (Folder FF42)
  - Medical Associations-Sons and Daughters of Hygiea, State of Massachusetts, circa 1900 (Folder FF42)
  - Medical Associations-Steuben County Medical Society, 1821 (Folder FF42)
- Series XIV: Memorial, 1872-1931
  This series is comprised of certificates from clubs and organizations honoring deceased members. These include certificates in memory of William de Groot from the Empire State Society, James C. Russell from the Coffee Exchange of the City of New York, and Edward L. Phalon from the John Bruning Bowling Club.
  Two certificates were printed to honor fallen Civil War soldiers, including one printed by Currier and Ives. Also included are certificates in memory of James P. Harper and John McEntee Bowman.
  Of special note is a memorial for Horace Greeley from the American Institute. This certificate is elaborately hand-lettered and includes an albumen portrait.
  - Coffee Exchange of the City of New York, 1913 (Folder FF43)
  - Farmer's Club of the American Institute, 1872 (Folder FF73)
  - German American Society, 1873 (Folder FF73)
  - Hotel Association of New York City, 1931 (Folder FF43)
  - John Bruning Bowling Club, undated (Folder FF43)
  - Lexington Avenue Church, undated (Folder FF43)
  - Sons of the American Revolution, 1899 (Folder FF43)
  - Veteran Corps, 1873 (Folder FF43)
- Series XV: Military, 1838-1946
  This series includes certificates given to commemorate appointments and changes in rank, citations and discharges from service, as well as membership to various clubs and organizations. It also includes certificates of recognition for donation of time or funds to various military causes. Some are printed on parchment with original seals.
  Certificates of appointment include several from both John Stoneacre Ellis and Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright. One certificate from Hempstead, Long Island dated 1819, acknowledges a soldiers enrollment in "a troop of horse artillery…comprising part of a brigade in the second regiment of the state of New York."
  A War Department certificate confirms pension payments owed to Revolutionary War widow Esther Hammond.
  Certificates of discharge include one for Fred W. Mather, member of the 24th Regiment, United Stated Colored Troops.
  Also included are several Civil War Soldiers Memorial certificates, which list names and ranks of regiment soldiers as well as their battle history.
  - Appointments- Army, 1921-1926 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Appointments- Army, 1866-1868, 1892, 1911 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- National Army Draft Board, 1917 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Appointments- National Guard, 1857-1920 (Folder FF45)
  - Appointments- Officers' Reserve Corps, 1921 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Appointments- San Francisco City Guard, undated (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- United States Merchant Marines, 1919 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- First California Guard, 1850-1861 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- Second Brigade of the Militia of the State of California, 1862 (Folder FF74)
  - Appointments- Second Irish Regiment, California Militia, 1864 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- Second Regiment of New York State, 1819 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- 12th Regiment of New York Volunteers, 1898 (Folder FF44)
  - Appointments- 66th Regiment of New York Volunteers, 1861 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Appointments- 29th Regiment of Pennsylvania Volunteers, 1862, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Citations- Albany Burgesses Corps, commemoration of the excursion to Newburgh, 1867 (Folder FF74)
  - Citations- American Expeditonary Forces Citation for Meritorious Service, 1918-1919 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- Army Ordnance Association Medal of Merit, 1937 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- Belgian "Croix de Guerre Belge" for Meritorious Service in Ypres, 1921 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- British War Mission, 1918 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- Commonwealth of Massachusetts Testimonial of Gratitude for Patriotism, 1870 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- County of Richmond (S.I.) Grateful Appreciation of Patriotic Service, 1919 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- Distinguished Service Medal, 1925-1926 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- "In Honour of the Commander of the American Forces in Defence of Plattsburg", 1814 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- New York National Guard, 9th Infantry Regiment testimonial, 1869 (Folder FF74)
  - Citations- New York State Cross for Conspicuous Service, 1937 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- New York State Decoration for Long and Faithful Service, 1899, 1928, 1935 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- Seventeenth Ward Volunteer Recruiting Committee, New York City testimonial, 1865 (Folder FF74)
  - Citations- United States Food Administration, in appreciation of patriotic service during the Great War., circa 1918 (Folder FF46)
  - Citations- United States War Department, for faithful service in the Ordnance Department, 1919 (Folder FF46)
  - Discharges- Army, 1865, 1919 (Folder FF47)
  - Discharges- Navy, 1862 (Folder FF47)
  - Discharges- New York State National Guard, 1861-1959 (Folder FF47)
  - Discharges- New York State National Guard, 1896 (Folder FF74)
  - Memorials- Army Memorial, 1864 (Folder FF75)
  - Memorials- New York State Volunteers, 1863 (Folder FF75)
  - Memorials- Ohio Volunteers, 1862 (Folder FF75)
  - Memorials- Soldiers Individual Memorial, 1866 (Folder FF75)
  - Memorials- Union Defenders, undated (Folder FF75)
  - Societies and Associations- Air Warden Service, 1942 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Societies and Associations- Albany Burgesses Corps, 1910 (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- Army of the Boys in Blue, 1884 (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- Disabled American Veterans of the World War, 1931 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Societies and Associations- Knickerbocker Greys, 1896-1898 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Societies and Associations- Military Order of the Loyal Legion, 1866-1905 (Folder FF77)
  - Societies and Associations- Military Philosophical Society, undated (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- Minute Men of America, 1942 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- National Security League, 1919 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- Navy League of the United States, 1918 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- New Jersey Union League, 1863 (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- New York Society Military and Naval Officers, 1933, 1938 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- New York War Fund, 1944 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Societies and Associations- Scott Life Guard of the City of New York, 1859 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- Society of the Army of the Potomac, undated (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- Society of California Volunteers, 1871 (Folder FF76)
  - Societies and Associations- Union Veteran Legion, 1903 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Societies and Associations- United Service Organizations (USO), 1946 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Societies and Associations- Veterans of the National Guard, 1876 (Folder FF76)
  - Other- War Department certificate showing pension payment owed to Revolutionary War widow, 1838 (Folder FF76)
- Series XVI: Political and Government, 1805-1994
  This series is comprised of certificates from various government and political organizations.
  Two certificates of appointment to federal positions have President Warren Harding's signature.
  Tammany Society (also known as the Columbian Order) certificates contain one printed by Samuel Maverick and two that are illustrated and hand-lettered. Certificates of membership to the Tippecanoe Club are printed with images of William Henry Harrison.
  One certificate of note was issued to Elisha Harris in recognition of his efforts to conduct the first sanitary survey of the city to try to combat cholera.
  - Government-Federal- appointment to Aide in the Inaguration Parade, 1901 (Folder FF48)
  - Government-Federal- appointment to Assistant Secretary of War, 1921 (Folder FF48)
  - Government-Federal- appointment to Pension Agent, 1886 (Folder FF48)
  - Government-Federal- appointment to the Advisory Committee at the Conference of Limitation of Armanent, 1921 (Folder FF48)
  - Government-Federal- appointment to the War Industries Board, 1918 (Folder FF48)
  - Government-Local- City of New York- appointment of Comptroller, 1934 (Folder FF49)
  - Government-Local- City of New York- appointment to committee for the commemoration of NYC's golden jubilee, 1948 (Folder FF49)
  - Government-Local- City of New York- Common Council, 1851, 1878 (Folder FF49)
  - Government-Local- City of New York- Common Council, 1861, 1863 (Folder Oversize FF 82)
  - Government - Local - City of New York - Accumulated Debt Bond, 1869, 1879 (Folder FF49)
    Bond for $2,000 issued to Mrs. H.G. Hawkins. Stamped on back as transferred to George H. Sistare's Sons in 1879. (Source: Gift from an anonymous donor, May 2019)
  - Government - Local - City of New York - Corporate Stock to Provide for the Supply of Water, 1906 (Folder FF49)
    Cancelled certificate. Issued to Matilda E. Webb. (Source: Gift from an anonymous donor, May 2019)
  - Government-Local- Nassau County- Proclamation in honor of 103rd birthday, 1994 (Folder FF49)
  - Government-State- New York- State Legislature resolution, 1859 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- appointment to the Commission to Revise Banking Law, 1913 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- appointment of Commissioner of Palisades Interstate Park, 1900-1901 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- appointment of State Historian, 1907 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- appointment of Workmen's Compensation Commission member, 1914 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- appointment of Military Secretary to the Governor, 1913 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New York- commemoration of "An Act to amend the Highway Law", 1913 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- New Jersey- appointment of commission member of Palisades Interstate Park, 1924 (Folder FF50)
  - Government-State- Pennsylvania- appointment to the Commission to Construct a Public Steamboat Landing, 1907 (Folder FF50)
  - Political Organizations- Citizen's Association of New York- recognition of the first sanitary survey of the city, 1867 (Folder FF78)
  - Political Organizations- Eleventh Ward Association of New York, in appreciation of Provost Marshal, 1865 (Folder Oversize FF 82)
  - Political Organizations- Loyal National League, 1863 (Folder FF78)
  - Political Organizations- Republican Party of the County of New York- poll watcher's certificate, 1943 (Folder FF78)
  - Political Organizations- Tammany Society, 1805-1897, undated (Folder FF78)
  - Political Organizations- Tippecanoe Club, 1840, undated (Folder FF78)
  - Political Organizations- Williamsbridge Democratic and Social Club, 1915 (Folder FF78)
- Series XVII: Regional and Ethnic, 1798-1930
  This series contains certificates of membership to societies with regional and/or ethnic interests. Certificates include the Caledonian Society of the City of New York, the Society of St. George and the South Carolina Society. The German Society certificate is written in German and has its original wax seal.
  Certificates of membership in the Cape Cod Association lithographs by Sarony, Major and Knapp and are heavily illustrated with maritime images as well as views of Provincetown, Massachusetts.
  Also of note is John Stoneacre Ellis' certificate of membership to the Associated Pioneers of the Territorial Days of California.
  - American Ethnological Society, 1903 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Associated Pioneers of the Territorial Days of California, 1878 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Caledonian Society of the City of New York, 1798 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cape Cod Association of the City of New York, undated (Folder FF79)
  - Columbia River Historical Expedition, 1926 (Folder FF79)
  - German Society certificate, 1830 (Folder FF79)
  - German Society certificate (framed), 1803 (Offsite-box 8)
    Gift of Frederick Baker, 2018.
  - Herkimer County Historical Society, 1910 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Hispanic Society of America, 1907 (Folder FF79)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1930 (Folder FF79)
  - New Hampshire Historical Society, 1927 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - New York Southern Society, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Society of St. George, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - South Carolina Society, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ticonderoga Historical Society, 1910 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Upper Missouri Historical Expedition, 1925 (Folder FF79)
- Series XVIII: Religious, 1809-1929
  This series includes certificates of baptism, communion and confirmation, as well as membership to various religious societies. Sunday school attendance and merit certificates are also part of this series.
  One certificate from the American Bible Union records contributions made to the group to distribute bibles to "the Freedmen of America." A group of ephemera related to the Domestic Missionary Army of the Young Soldiers of Christ of the Protestant Episcopal Church includes a ribbon printed with the portrait of Jackson Kemper. Temperance certificates include membership to the Boston Temperance Society, the Washington Temperance Society, and several Juvenile Temperance Societies. One particularly interesting certificate is a certificate of membership for the Connecticut Cold Water Army, which includes songs of the Cold Water Army. Early membership certificates for the American Bible Society include those for Mrs. John McComb, Jr. and Gerard Beekman.
  Related Materials
  N-YHS also holds about 70 marriage (mostly), baptism, confirmation, and death certificates in the Jon Charles Acker collection of religious certificates (PR 360).
  - Bible and Tract Societies- American Bible Society, 1830-1874 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bible and Tract Societies- American Bible Society, 1856, undated (Folder FF51)
  - Bible and Tract Societies- American Bible Union, 1868 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bible and Tract Societies- American Tract Society, 1826 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bible and Tract Societies- American Tract Society, 1835-1881 (Folder FF51)
  - Bible and Tract Societies- New York Bible Society, 1892 (Folder FF51)
  - Missionary Societies- American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1856 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1898 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- American Home Missionary Society, 1828 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- American Protestant Society, 1848 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- American Sunday School Union, 1850-1851 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- Children's Missionary Society, 1873-1874 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- Diocesan Missionary Society (Protestant Episcopal), 1854 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- Domestic Missionary Army of the Young Soldiers of Christ, 1868 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- Maine Missionary Society, 1863 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- Mission of the Immaculate Virgin-St. Joseph's Union, 1929 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- Presbyterian Church Five Million Memorial Fund, 1871 (Folder FF52)
  - Missionary Societies- United Foreign Missionary Society, 1822, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Missionary Societies- Universalist Missionary Army, 1871 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sacramental Certificates- Baptism, Communion, Confirmation, Marriage, 1849-1901 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
  - Sacramental Certificates- Baptism, Communion, Confirmation, 1897-1935 (Folder FF 52-A)
  - Sunday School Certificates, 1809-1838 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Sunday School Certificates, 1826-1883 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
  - Temperance Societies- Boston Temperance Societies, 1843 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Temperance Societies- Connecticut Cold Water Army, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Temperance Societies- Juvenile Temperance Society, 1841 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Temperance Societies- Methodist Episcopal School Temperance Society, 1842 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Temperance Societies- Temperance Society of the Sabbath School of Laight St. Church, 1836 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Temperance Societies- Washington Temperance Society, 1842 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
- Series XIX: Scientific, 1819-1945
  This series contains certificates of membership to societies such as the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the National Geographic Society, the New York Academy of Science, and the New York Zoological Society.